J. Bankston Papers, 1950-1985 MS 447
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
J. Bankston Papers 1950-1985 (bulk 1980-1985)
Collection Number: MS 447
Bankston, J.
1.5 linear feet
Documents from Court Case No. C79-0515 “Irene Allen, et. al. plaintiffs vs. United States of America” related to nuclear testing by the United States government in the 1950s in Nevada that affected people in Arizona, Nevada and Utah. The bulk of the material consists of the court case, personal digests, technical reports and articles used by Jay Bankston to aid him in his application to the Veterans Administration for compensation for cancer he believed was the result of exposure to radiation during his military service in the Marshall Islands.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
None
Biographical Note
J. Bankston was born December 23, 1926 in El Dorado, Arkansas, died April 22, 1997 in Bisbee, Arizona. Marine Sgt. Jarrell M. “J” Banskton served on active duty with the United States Navy from July 1944 to October 1947, and then with the United States Marines from July 1950 to May 1951. He served aboard the USS Albemarle, a seaplane base in the Marshall Islands in July 1946 where he worked on the assembly and handling of test units for nuclear detonations. The collection covers a court case and other documentation about radioactive fallout and its effects. Bankston used the material to submit a case for compensation to the Veterans Administration for a cancerous tumor he believed was caused by exposure to radiation during the “Operation Crossroads” detonation in July of 1946 in the Marshall Islands.
This collection is organized into 4 series.
I: Correspondence, 1980-1982.
II: Court Case, 1979-1980.
III: Digests, circa 1982.
IV: Newspaper Articles & Reports, 1948-1970.
Correspondence, Court Case documents, Newspaper Articles and Technical Reports. The bulk of the collection relates to the federal trial brought against the United States by Irene Allen and about 1200 other plaintiffs for radiation poisoning caused by nuclear testing by the United States in Nevada in the 1950s. Stewart L. Udall is listed as an attorney for Irene Allen, et. al. or the “Downwinders” as they were known. The “Downwinders” were plaintiffs from the states of Arizona, Nevada and Utah in the 1982 federal trial that was unsuccessful in getting compensation for the plaintiffs. This trial eventually led to the passing of the Radiation Exposure Compensation Act of 1990 that provides monetary compensation for people who develop cancer as a result of exposure to atmospheric nuclear testing. The digests and technical reports are research material used by Bankston in his attempt to receive compensation for cancer he believed he got as a result of his assignment to duty aboard the USS Albemarle while in the Marine Corps. He believed he was exposed to radiation when he worked on the preparations aboard the ship for “Operation Crossroads”, a major nuclear detonation in the Marshall Islands in July of 1946. The ship was within a 155 mile distance from the air and undersea tests conducted by the US Navy. Correspondence is directly related to his unsuccessful application for compensation with the Veterans Administration and with other veterans in various stages of applying for compensation. Bankston also corresponded with Arizona Senator Barry Goldwater to get support on his behalf with the Veterans Administration. In 1980 he became regional coordinator with the National Association of Atomic Veterans for the state of Arizona in order to represent atomic veterans and their widows.
Bankston, Jay; Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-1998 -- Correspondence.; Udall, Stewart L.; Albemarle (Seaplane base AV-5); National Association of Atomic Veterans.; United States. Radiation Exposure Compensation Act.; United States. Board of Veteran's Appeals.; United States. Marine Corps.; United States. Veteran's Administration.; Atmospheric radiation -- Marshall Islands.; Atomic bomb -- Marshall Islands -- Testing.; Downwinders; Liability for nuclear damages -- Arizona.; Nuclear explosions -- Marshall Islands.; Nuclear weapons -- Marshall Island.; Nuclear weapons testing victims -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Arizona.; Operation Crossroads, Marshall Islands, 1946.; Radiation carcinogenesis.; Radiation -- Health aspects.; Radiation -- Testing.; Radiation victims -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Arizona.; Radioactive fallout -- Arizona.; Radioactive fallout -- Nevada.; Radioactive fallout -- Utah.; Veterans -- Health aspects -- Arizona.; Veterans -- Diseases -- Government policy -- United States.; Veterans -- Medical care.; Bikini Atoll (Marshall Islands) -- Environmental conditions.; Kwajalein Island (Marshall Islands) -- Environmental conditions.; Marshall Islands -- Environmental conditions.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1980-1982
  - Goldwater, Barry M., Senator, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Haralson, Dale, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Karasti, Frank, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Kelly, Wanda S., National Association of Atomic Veterans, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - King, Eugene P.1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mehas, Thomas C., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Shuman, Sydney J., Veteran's Administration, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Court Case, 1979-1980
  - Case No. C79-0515 "Irene Allen, et. al. plaintiffs vs. United States of America" - Memorandum Opinion, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Case No. C79-0515 "Irene Allen, et. al. plaintiffs vs. United States of America" - Proposed Findings of Fact and Conclusion of Law, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Case No. C79-0515 "Irene Allen, et. al. plaintiffs vs. United States of America" - Plaintiff's Amended Proposed Findings of Fact and Conclusion of Law, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Case No. C79-0515 "Irene Allen, et. al. plaintiffs vs. United States of America" - Exhibits, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Case No. C79-0515 "Irene Allen, et. al. plaintiffs vs. United States of America" - Trail Memorandum Exhibits Relating to Cedar City Sheep Exposure, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - List of Defendants Exhibits not furnished to the Plaintiff, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Plaintiffs' Opening Statement, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Testimony by Dorothy B. Jones before House Committee on Interstate and Foreign Commerce, Subcommittee on Health and the Environment, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series III: Digests, circa 1982
  - Digests: Author Index, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Digests I (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Digests II (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Digests III, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Digests: Notes, circa 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Digests: Reel Digest-Microfilm, circa 1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Digests: Subject Index, circa 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Newspaper articles and technical reports, 1948-1980
  - Newspaper Articles: Arizona Daily Star &Tucson Citizen, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reports, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reports, 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reports I, 1953-1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Reports II, 1953-1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Reports, 1954-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reports, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Symposium on Sol-Gel Processes &Reactor Fuel Cycles, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)